Inventory of the James B. Mason papers
Hoover Institution Archives
James B. Mason papers
1942-1952
XX161
Hoover Institution Archives
1 folder, 1 envelope (0.2 linear feet)
Reports and photographs, relating to American military medical activities in the European Theater during World War II.
Mason, James B.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Brigadier general, United States Army Medical Corps; liaison officer, Chief Surgeon's Office, European Theater of Operations, during World War II.
Scope and Content of Collection
Reports and photographs, relating to American military medical activities in the European Theater during World War II.
United States. Army Medical Service.; World War, 1939-1945--Medical care.
- European Theater of Operation (ETO) Office of the Chief Surgeon documents, 1942-1944 (Folder 1)
  - Orientation report to the Army Surgeon General from Col. Mason of ETO
  - Whole Blood Service ETO Charts, drafts of letters, memoradums, personnel requirements (organization chart) and equipment list
  - Medical station list, 20 November 1943
  - Chart of Medical Troop Strength ETO, June-October 1942
  - Annual Report Chief Operations and Training Division to Chief Surgeon ETO, 15 January 1943 for period June-December 31, 1942
  - Memo to Chief Surgeon--Hospitalization/Evacuation estimates for "Operation Overlord"
  - Beach Medical Service in U.K. Draft, May 1943
  - Evacuation in cross channel operations
  - Working copy, inspection trip to Southampton, 31 March 1943
  - 1 & 2 Chronological History, Operations Division Office Chief Surgeon ETO 25 May (working copy)
  - Projected bed requirements and forecast of beds available 30 September 1943-30 April 1944
  - Draft of Medical operational plan for "Round-Up", 28 May 1942
  - ETO Medical Troop Basis, December 1943 (2 parts)
  - Report to Professional Service Division, office Chief Surgeon ETO, 28 March 1944
  - Historical Notes 805th Hospital Center ETOUSA, 13 March 1952
  - Photo of Major General Hawley, Chief Surgeon ETO and citation for Gorges award 1947 (pamphlet), 6 photos with captions on reverse, ETO Medical activity
  - Memorandum of Guidance from General Omar N. Bradley to FIRST Army and to ADSEC, April 1944
  - Policy Statement on Command Channels ADSEC
  - Situation Report as of 6 April 1945 (ADSEC)
  - Copy Venereal Disease Control Survey of Armentiers, France, 20 September 1944
- Photographs (Envelope A)
  34 prints depicting scenes of the activities of the Medical Service Advance Section Communication Zone of the European Theater of Operations, including air evacuations, hospitals, supply depots, and charts of general medical operations and needs. Belgium, France.
  - Aerial evacuation of ADSEC Units in Belgium (2 prints)
  - 13 photos of hospitals in 818th Hospital, Center, Liege, Belgium
  - 6 photos of Supply Depot Operations in Liege, Belgium
  - 3 copies of prints of Medical Depot of German Army Group B at Reims, France
  - 6 copies of Briefing Charts ADSEC: Preventative Medicine, Operations, Operations distribution of whole blood June 1944-May 1945, Evacuation June 1944-May 1945, Evacuation log by modality 6 June 1944-10 June 1945, Supply showing locations of depots
  - 4 maps of hopital centers under ADSEC: 808 in Aachen (Col. T.J. Hartford), 819 in Bar le Duc/Verdun (Col. S.F. Seeley), 818 in Liege (Col. R.B. Hill), 820 in Nancy (Col. Paul Crawford)